The Shimogamo Shrine is located
高野川と賀茂川に挟まれた
三角地帯に位置する下鴨神社
in the triangular area surrounded by the Takano and Kamo rivers.
"Lake Biwa"
Although there are mountains of shrines with noble lineages in Kyoto,
京都に　由緒正しき神社は山ほど　あれど
"Kamo River"
"Takano River"
Shimogamo Shrine is one of the foremost
中でも下鴨神社は　平安以前から
存在する屈指の大神社である
"Shimogamo Shrine"
among the ones that existed prior to the Heian period.
Though scores of visitors go there throughout the year
縁結びをはじめ様々な御神徳を得るべく
"God of matchmaking Aioi Shrine"
to receive matchmaking and all kinds of other blessings from the gods,
年間　多くの参拝客が訪れるが
そのかいわいに　夜な夜なある屋台ラーメンが
出没することはあまり　知られていない
few know that a small ramen cart appears in the vicinity each and every night.
It's called Neko Ramen.
名を猫ラーメンといい
猫で　だしを取っているという
噂のラーメンであるが
The rumor is it uses actual cats to make the broth,
真偽の程は　定かでない
しかし　その味は無類である
but whether that's true or not cannot be ascertained.
However, the taste is unmatched.
（ラーメンを　すする音）
You are a person of Shimogamo Yuusuisou, yes?
貴君　下鴨幽水荘の人だろう
In fact I am a resident of Shimogamo Yuusuisou.
いかにも　わたしは
下鴨幽水荘の住人である
そうですが
Yes, and...?
I also live there.
わたしも　住んでいる
Shimogamo Yuusuisou is a boarding house behind Eizan Demachiyanagi Station,
下鴨幽水荘とは
えいざん出町柳裏にある下宿で
and it's apparently exactly the same as it was since it was rebuilt after it disappeared
聞いたところによると　幕末の混乱期に焼失して
再建以後　そのままであるという
during the violence of the final days of the Tokugawa shogunate.
窓から明かりが漏れていなければ
廃虚同然
If it weren't for the light leaking out the windows, it would be no different than ruins,
and when I visited there at the introduction of the University Co-op at the start of school,
入学したばかりのころ大学生協の紹介で
ここを訪れたとき
It's no wonder I thought I'd accidentally stumbled into Kowloon City.
九龍城に迷い込んだのかもと思ったのも　無理からぬ話だ
Ah, that's it!
そうだ　この奇妙な怪人を幾度か見掛けていたことを思い出した
I remembered that I have spotted this queer, curious fellow quite a number of times.
I am a god of Shimogamo Shrine.
わたしは　下鴨神社の神だ
My proper name is Kamotaketsunuminokami.
正確に言うと　賀茂建角身神だ
K-Kamotake?
（噴き出す音）
か…　かもたけ
Kamotaketsunominokamo.
「かもたけつのみのかも」だ
Don't make me say it twice.
２度も言わすな
But the second time was different...
いや　１回目と違って…
You didn't know?
知らんのか？
I know everything about you.
わたしは　君のことなら
何でも知っている
Your parents' names, how you were always throwing up and making sour smells as a baby,
ご両親の名前や
しょっちゅう　ゲロ吐いて　いつも酸っぱい
においのする　赤ん坊だったこと
小学校時代の　あだ名
your nickname during elementary school, the middle school cultural festival,
中学校時代の学園祭
高校時代の淡い初恋
your fleeting first love during high school, the first time you watched an adult video,
初めての　アダルトビデオ
浪人時代
your life as a ronin, and your lazy, idle days spent after entering college.
大学に入ってからの
怠惰で無為な日々
嘘だ
You've got to be kidding me!
夢見たサークルで　恋に破れ
After suffering romantic disappointment in the club of your dreams, unable to open up to people,
人と打ち解けられず　やがて
人の恋路を邪魔するようになった
before long you started getting in the way of people's path to love.
And why have you spent these two years in such a timid state?
何故　そんな　いじける一方の
２年間を過ごしてしまったのか…
それは　小津が…
That's because Ozu...
I accept that you have had your soul somewhat dirtied by the influence of Ozu.
貴君が小津の薄汚れた魂に
影響されたことは　認めよう
But that is not all, is it?
しかし　それだけではないだろう？
The past two years go rambling through my brain like swaying paper lanterns.
わたしの脳裏を来し方２年の
むにゃむにゃが走馬灯のように流れた
よりによって神聖なる下鴨神社の森で
At the sacred woods of Shimogamo Shrine, of all places,
my delicate heart was seized by painful memories, and...
とげだらけの思い出に繊細なハートを
わしづかみにされかけ　わたしは
ぎゃあああ
"Ahhhh!"
...is what I wanted to scream out, but I restrained myself like a gentleman.
と　叫びたくなったが
紳士らしく耐えた
N-None of your business. It's got nothing to do with you.
お…　大きな　お世話だ
あんたには　何も関係がない
It will soon be Kannazuki.
もうじき神無月だ
I must travel to Izumo once again.
また出雲へと
行かなくてはならない
It is our job, yes, but it is quite a lot of work, and don't make light of the train fare.
それがわれわれの仕事だが
手間もかかるし　電車代もバカにならぬ
In this age we just toss everyone's proposals
このご時世　それぞれ
持ち寄った案件を
into the wooden box for "already inspected" with hardly a look.
そのまま　審査済みの木箱へと
放り込んでいくばかりだ
And yet as I am a serious fellow,
それでも　根がまじめな　わたしは
ついつい深入りし
I can't help but to be deep in thought, scratching my head
一人一人にふさわしい出会いについて
じっくり考え　頭をかきむしる
thinking about which two people would be most suited for each other,
almost like a matrimonial agency.
まるで　結婚相談所だ
Woe is me.
嘆かわしい
Don't you think?
そう思わないか？　君
I don't follow in the slightest.
話が　全然見えません
When fall comes we gather at Izumo,
秋になれば　われわれは
出雲に集まって　男女の縁を決める
and decide the relationships of men and women.
Here is the name Akashi-san, whom you know.
ここに　君の知っている
明石さんの名前がある
And here are you and the name Ozu.
そして　こちらに
君と小津の名前
Do you understand?
分かるかい？
Understand what?
どういうことですか？
You're even stupider than I thought.
思いのほか　アホだな
わたしは　縁結びの神として
君の知っている女性
As a god of matchmaking,
I am preparing to match this woman you know, Akashi-san, with someone.
明石さんとの縁を
誰かと結ぼうとしている
In other words, it's between you and Ozu-kun.
要するに
貴君か小津君かの　どちらかだ
If you desire, come to my room.
希望があれば
わたしの部屋へ来なさい
Shimogamo Yuusuisou, room 210.
下鴨幽水荘の２１０号室だ
This strange fellow is saying he is trying to tie Akashi-san to either Ozu or me.
この怪人は　明石さんをわたしか
小津のどちらかと結び付けると言う
Humans hide their faces in front of thick clouds
hitobito wa atsui kumo ni kao wo kakushiteru
人々は厚い雲で顔を隠してる
Getting more and more consumed by the feeling of getting nowhere
iki ba no nai omoi wo zutto motte toideiru
行き場のない想いをずっと持って研いでいる
Even now, they're still buried in the same empty town
nani mo nai machi ni umorete mo sore demo ima demo
何もない街に埋もれても それでも 今でも
A perfect dream of dolls lined up
tsuranaru uindou ni
連なるウィンドウに
on a stretched out window
narabitatsu ningyou no marui yume
並び立つ人形の悪い夢
Then they hide themselves away
sore to mo soko ni kakurete
それとも倉庫に隠れて
so that they can be covered up
fusaidetatte
塞いでたって
Wearing only their pride, they still can't find anything
hokori dake kabutte mitsukaranai
埃だけ被って見つからない
They still aren't touched, no matter whose hands they're in
dare no te ni datte furerarenai
誰の手にだって触れられない
If we repeat this moment of ours properly,
boku tachi no genzai wo kurikaesu koto darake demo
僕たちの現在を繰り返すことだらけでも
I will meet you someday
sou itsuka kimi to deaou
そういつか君と出会おう
Until that day is here, I will keep on going
sonna hi wo omotte hibi wo ikou
そんな日を思って 日々を行こう
Going
ikou
行こう
When I was in high school I didn't participate in any club activities
高校のころは特に　クラブ活動もせず
同じような非活動的な男たちと
くすぶっているばかりだった
and just stayed cooped up with a bunch of other layabout guys.
But now I was a brand-spanking new freshman university student.
しかし　わたしは
ぴかぴかの大学１回生
幻の至宝といわれる「ばら色のキャンパスライフ」への扉が
今ここに　無数に開かれているのを目の当たりにし
and countless doors to the mystical treasure that is known as
that "rose-colored campus life" lay open before me.
興奮半ば　もうろうとしていた
I was half-swooned with glee.
And the one I chose was...
そして
わたしが選びとったのは…
"Cupid"
Among the raven-haired maidens working up an invigorating sweat,
黒髪の乙女たちと
さわやかに汗を流しながら
恋のラリーを打ち合うのだ！
I would begin the rally of love!
...is what I, a fool beyond all help, had thought.
そう考えていた　わたしは
手の施しようのない　アホだった
The first summer.
１回生の夏
My still-as-of-yet rose-colored self was cut to the quick by that which is called reality.
まだ　それなりに　ばら色であったわたしの脳みそを
現実という鋭い　やいばが　一閃した
Making 100 friends wouldn't be so bad, or so I frivolously thought,
友達１００人できるのも悪くないと高をくくっていたが
but I was soon made aware that just how difficult casually getting to know other people could be.
人と　さわやかに交流することが
いかに難しいかを　思い知らされた
My wish of a rally unfulfilled, I was not even able to hit back,
ラリーどころか　まともに打ち返すことも
かなわず　打ったボールは　返ってこない
and my serves were left unreturned.
柔軟な社交性を身に付けようにも
そもそも　会話の中に入れない
I tried training myself to be sociable and easy-going,
but I wasn't part of the conversation to begin with.
By the time I realized I had to be sociable in order to be included in the conversation,
会話に加わるための社交性をどこか
よそで身に付けてくる必要があった
と気付いたときにはすでに手遅れであり
it was already too late. I had lost my place among the circle.
わたしはサークルで居場所を失っていた
It was then that an ominous man stood beside me with a face of ill portent.
そのとき　わたしの傍らにひどく
縁起の悪そうな顔をした不気味な男が立っていた
Are you some messenger from hell that only delicate little me can see?
これは　繊細なわたしだけに見える　地獄からの使者か？
You say some pretty mean things.
あなた　ひどいこと　おっしゃる
There's no need to worry, I am your compatriot!
ご安心ください
僕は　あなたの同志ですよ
That was my first contact with Ozu, as well as worst contact.
これが小津とのファーストコンタクトであり
ワーストコンタクトでもあった
Anyway, it's quite a contrast, isn't it?
それにしても　これは見事に　明暗を分けましたねぇ
Maybe I should mix it up over there myself.
いっそ　僕も向こうに　交ざっちゃおうかな
"Shimogamo Shrine"
The place where the Kamo and Takano rivers join
下鴨神社を下った高野川
賀茂川の合流地点は「鴨川デルタ」と呼ばれ
below the Shimogamo Shrine is referred to as the "Kamo River Delta,"
"Us, Concealed"  "Party Area"
春から夏にかけてのコンパ会場として
広く利用されていた
and is widely used as a party location for celebrating the beginning of summer.
Ozu is in the same year I am.
小津は　わたしと同学年である
夜道で会えば１０人中８人は　妖怪と間違え
8 in 10 people who saw him in the dark would mistake him for a youkai,
"Hates vegetables"
"Grades
dangerously low"
"Selfish"
"No pride"
"Lazy"
"Picks on the weak"
"The devil"
２人は　妖怪と納得する
and the remaining two could be convinced of it.
"Sucks up to the strong"
"Doesn't care as
long as it's funny"
"Fast at
running
away"
"Worthless
character"
Eating the unhappiness of the others as a topping on his rice,
他人の不幸をおかずにして飯が食える
およそ　褒めるべきところが一つもない男だ
he's a man with seriously not a single point of praise.
My soul would have surely stayed unblemished were it not for having met him.
もし　彼と出会わなければ
きっと　わたしの魂はもっと清らかだったであろう
Hey, are you gonna turn on me?
おい　裏切るのか？
I'm just joking with you.
冗談ですよ
うっ…　くっつくな
Stop touching me!
But the night breeze is so chilly...
だって　夜風が冷たいんだもの
この　寂しがり屋さんが！
You lonely bastard!
Damn it... Why does it have to be you next to me instead of a raven-haired maiden?
くそ…　なぜ　わたしの隣が
黒髪の乙女じゃなく　お前なんだ！
Oh, look. Akashi-san came, too.
おや　明石さんも来てますねえ
ほら　あそこ
See, over there.
Let me see!
貸せ
She's in the engineering department, so maybe she's designing for Birdman or something.
彼女　工学部だからバードマンの設計
やってるんじゃないかな
Hey, maybe we should call it off for today...
おい　今日は　やめにしないか？
明石さんを巻き添えにするのは…。
I don't want to get Akashi-san mixed up in this.
What are you saying?
What happened to your pride as a "Black Cupid"?
何を言ってるんです
「黒いキューピッド」としての
誇りは　どうしました！
Well, sure I have my pride, but to someone from the outside, this just looks like...
もちろん　誇りはあるが
世間の人から見ればこれは　ただの…
You're going to let your conviction bend because you're worried about what other people think?
世間の目を気にして
信念を　折り曲げるんですか？
僕が　身も心も捧げたのは
そんな人じゃありませんね
Well I, who have dedicated both my body and soul, am not a person such as that.
Are you not here today precisely because you bare this loneliness and isolation?
孤独と偏見に耐えてきたからこそ
今のあなたがあるんじゃないですか
They are the ones that have lost sight of reality!
彼らは
現実を見失っているんです！
You must bring the hammer down upon those who have lost themselves among frivolous dreams!
あなたが　軽佻浮薄な夢に
浮かれる者たちに鉄ついを下さねば！
Now, without further ado!
さあ　いざ！
Hear ye, hear ye! For we are the ones who hinder love!
やあやあ
われこそは　恋の邪魔者！
浮かれた諸君に向けて
これより　天誅を下す！
We will now rain the heavens down upon you merrymaking ladies and gentlemen!
あ
ほ
Id... iot...
あ…　ほ…
Yes, we may be idiots, but you guys should watch out for us!
そうとも　われはアホなり！
君たち　くれぐれも
目には　注意するように！
（花火の音）
（悲鳴）
Bottle rocket fireworks are for the purpose of rocketing up into the night sky.
打ち上げ花火というものは夜空に
打ち上げるべきものである
"Bottle rockets, roman candles and firecrackers are not allowed"
Doing things like holding them in your hand,
決して　手に持ったり　人に向けたり
川向こうで和気あいあいとコンパをしている
人たちを爆撃するのに　使ってはいけない
aiming them at people, or using them to bomb people over rivers
having a peaceful harmonious party is quite not allowed.
Hold your ground! Counterattack!
ひるむな　反撃しろー
Oh?
あれ？
You damn barbarians!
この　狼藉者めがーっ！
That's one shallow river!
川　浅っ！
We're gonna smack you good!
手打ちにしてくれる！
Hey, Ozu, they're not all out!
おい　小津！　まだ火が！
Hey!
Since I had met Ozu it was just cutting, cutting, and more cutting
小津と知り合ってからの
わたしは安井金比羅宮もかくやと
the red threads that stretched across the circle like at Yasui-konpiragu.
サークル内に張り巡らされた赤い糸を
切って　切って　切りまくった
"Fatty"
At these activities Ozu was ingenious,
こうした　工作活動にかけて小津は天才的であり
and there were even villainous rumors
およそ　破廉恥な噂ならば知らぬ事はない
という独自の情報網を駆使して
that there was no personal information we did not know and make use of,
and that we would scatter oil and then light fires,
わたしが　油をまくそばから火を付けて回り
ある事ない事吹聴して
and whether that was true or not it was spread around
"Baldy"
常にサークル内のどこかで修羅場の炎が
燃えさかるという彼好みの環境をつくり上げた
and it was an environment where we were set up as guys
who constantly enjoyed blazing scenes of carnage here and there inside the circle.
まさに　悪の権化にふさわしい
ホモサピエンスの　面汚しである
Like some incarnation of evil, a disgrace among all homo sapiens.
Even after we were kicked out of the circle,
サークルを追われた後も
わたしたちの活動は緩むことなく
we did not let our activities slacken, we expanded globally,
さらに　グローバルに展開され　死に神のいでたちをした
「黒いキューピッド」としてその悪名をとどろかせた
and cloaked as gods of death the evil name of the "Black Cupids" roared throughout the land.
東に　恋する乙女がいれば
「あんな変態やめろ」と言い
If there was a maiden in love in the east we'd say "Give up on that freak,"
or for a man in the west worried about one-sided love we'd advise
西に　片思いに悩む男がいれば
「無駄なことはやめておけ」と助言する
"Just give up, it's no use."
南で　恋の火花が散りかけていれば
すぐさま水を掛けてやり
If the spark of love was sprinkled in the south, we'd immediately pour water on it,
and it's said love in the north is impossible to begin with.
北では　常に恋愛無用論を説いた
Sometimes our victims came close to drowning us in the canals of Lake Biwa,
ときに　被害者に危うく
琵琶湖疏水に沈められそうになり
下宿を包囲され　北白川の漫画喫茶で息を殺し
surrounded the boarding house, made me hide in a manga cafe in Kitashirakawa,
or cried at me in the middle of Konoe Street when I spoke too frankly.
直截にものを言い過ぎて
近衛通の路上で泣かれたりした
But I didn't lose, I couldn't lose,
しかしわたしは　負けなかった
負けることができなかった
しかし　負けていた方　がわたしも
みんなも幸せになれたに　違いない！
even though I was sure that losing would have let me and everyone else be happier!
Except for Ozu. I could care less if he's happy!
小津は幸せにならなくても　よい！！
As I was walking, catching my breath after having run all the way to Kiyamachi,
木屋町まで逃げ切ったわたしが
息を整え歩いていると
under the overhang of someone's house
民家の軒下から
怪しげな妖気を垂れ流している
老婆が　わたしを捉えた
I was caught by an old woman who emitted a suspiciously ghoulish aura.
This unplaceable aura was persuasive, and thinking logically,
その　えたいのしれない妖気には説得力があり
わたしは　論理的に考えた
there was no way that the fortune-telling of a creature
これだけの妖気を　無料で垂れ流している人物
の占いが当たらないわけがないと
who emits such an aura could be anything but spot on.
What do you want to know?
何を聞きたいんじゃ？
Your face is a face of extreme impatience... You are unsatisfied.
あなたの顔は大変もどかしいという顔
不満ですね
あなたは　才能を生かす環境に
恵まれていないと　感じています
I can feel that you are not blessed with a situation
where you can make the most of your talents.
Yes, that's exactly right!
そうなんです。
まさに　そのとおり
I can sense your fiercely earnest talent.
あなたは大変まじめで
才能もおありのようじゃし
老婆の彗眼に
わたしは早くも脱帽した
Quickly did I tip my hat to the old woman's keen insight.
To perceive my good sense and talents in an instant and yet be so very unassuming,
能ある鷹が　爪を隠すがごとく
つつましく　隠し過ぎたせいで
like how a master always hides their true ability, it made even me forget where I was.
自分でも所在が分からなくなっていた
わたしの良識と才能を
一目で見抜くとは
Anyway, I sense there is an opportunity you can't let pass by.
とにかく好機を逃さないことが肝心じゃ
An opportunity?
好機？
As in an excellent chance.
好機というのはよい機会ということじゃ
それは　分かってます
Yes, I know what it means...
This opportunity is always dangling in front of your eyes.
好機は　いつでもあなたの目の前に
ぶら下がってございます。
You must grab this opportunity and act on it.
あなたは　その好機を捉えて
行動に出なくちゃいけません
It's still somewhat vague.
んー　やけに漠然としてますね。
もっと具体的に
Can you be more specific?
And if you do not!
さもな！　い！　と！
You will walk this life as now, ever unchanging.
あなたはまた　今と変わらぬ
人生を歩むことじゃろう
That'll be 1,000 yen.
はい　１，０００円
But you haven't answered anything yet!
まだ　何も解決してないのに！
迷える小羊ごっこですか？
Playing the lost lamb?
A friend of yours, Ozu-kun?
小津君の　お友達？
You shameless bastard!
この　破廉恥野郎！
How the hell are you popular all of a sudden?
あの　モテモテぶりはどういうことだ！
Now that's just uncalled for.
あなた　ちょっと
八つ当りが過ぎますよ
こんな菌の塊　わたしに食わせて
Force feeding me such a bundle of fungi?
What is with these ribbed bits?
何すか？　このヒダヒダは？
She's the dental hygienist at the dentist I go to.
あれは　僕の通ってる歯医者の
歯科衛生士なんです
She looked totally drunk and asked me out for drinks.
すっかり酔っぱらってたみたいで
飲みに誘われたんですよ
Dentist?
歯医者…
And what about you?
あなたも　どうです？
I bet you've never had a young lady like that stick her fingers
あんな　若い女性が　指を口に
突っ込んでくれる機会なんて
あなたには　一生ないでしょう
in your mouth your entire life, right?
Don't bring me down to your level.
一緒にするな
そこまで落ちたくない
Oh, yeah?
知ってますよ　あなたが下鴨神社の
縁結びの神に　お参りしてること
I know you visited the god of matchmaking at the Shimogamo Shrine.
I just wanted to do it once for fun!
あれは　座興で一度やっただけだ
Speaking of which, what do you think of Akashi-san?
そういえば　あなた
明石さんて　どうなんです？
In other words, it's between you and Ozu-kun.
要するに
貴君か小津君かの　どちらかだ
What do I think?
どうって
I had thought I was the only person unfortunate enough
あなたという　アホな人間を理解できてしまう不幸な人は
これまで僕しかいなかったわけだけれども
to actually be able to comprehend a human being as dumb as yourself, but...
やかましい
Shush, you.
I think she might go out with you.
彼女には
できてしまいそうなんだな…
This is an opportunity!
これは　好機ですよ
Now look here.
あのね　俺は　俺のような人間を理解できる人より
I'd much rather have a beautiful raven-haired maiden
ふはふはーっとして美しいものだけで
頭がいっぱいの黒髪の乙女がいい
that makes you go "whoa..." than someone who is able to comprehend a person such as myself.
Why so selfish?
また　そんなワガママを言う
Don't tell me you're still hung up on being dumped by Kohinata-san?
まさか　１回生の時に小日向さんに振られた事
まだこだわっているんじゃないでしょうね
when we were freshmen, right?
Say not that name in my presence.
その名前を　口に出すな
Then I'll become happy in your place.
じゃあ　あんたの代わりに
幸せになってやろ
この好機　僕が　とっちまおう
I'll take this opportunity.
Now see here. Akashi-san is not interested in you.
言ってろ
明石さんはお前などに　興味はない
Don't give me that depressed look.
不景気な顔はやめましょうよ
I pray for your victory.
戦勝祝いですよ
Shut up!
うるさい
Thanks to you I've wasted my perfectly lovely college life.
お前のせいで　有意義な学生生活が
台無しになってしまった
あらら　それはお互いさまじゃありませんか。
Oh? I think you're also to blame for that.
どうせ　あなたは
どんな道を選んだって
After all, it doesn't matter which path you took,
今みたいな　ありさまに
なっちまうんだ
you'd keep ending up right where you are now.
At any rate, once I met you I put all my efforts into making you no good.
いずれにせよ僕は　あなたに出会って
全力で　あなたを駄目にします
Why do you haunt me so?
お前は　なぜわたしに　付きまとうのだ？
It's the way I show my love! We're connected by the black thread of fate, after all.
僕なりの　愛ですよ
われわれは運命の黒い糸で
結ばれてるというわけです
"The Japan Trench"
A chill went down my spine as a fearsome phantom rose into my mind.
恐るべき幻影が脳裏に浮かび
わたしは戦慄した
Senpai, if you want to eat any more, please hurry.
先輩　もっと
食べたければ　急いでください
Akashi-san, why are you here?
明石さん？　なぜ君がここに
You really are pretty dense, aren't you?
本当に先輩は　工夫がない人ですね
This is the usual place for the after-party, yes?
ここは　二次会の
定番じゃありませんか
The Birdman Circle is camped out over there.
先ほどの　バードマンサークルが
あちらに　陣取っております
I haven't eaten meat in a while so if you don't mind...
お肉は　久しぶりなので
わたしも　失礼
Meat after a party? Do they have no pride as agricultural people?
宴会の後で　肉とは
農耕民族としての誇りはないのか
あっ　小津は？
Where's Ozu?
He already ran out the back door.
すでに　裏口からお逃げになりました
You escape too, Senpai.
先輩も　お逃げください
That bastard's left me behind again!
あの野郎
またもわたしを差し置いて
I will handle the bill, so go out the back. That's what I came to say.
精算は　わたしが
済ませておきましたので　裏から
話は　通してあります
I'm in your debt.
この借りは　いずれ
借りは　いいですから
約束を　果たしてください
Forget about the debt, just keep your promise.
Never mind. Hurry and leave, I have to get back.
もういいです　お早く
わたしも戻ります
I met Akashi-san the previous year during a part time job at the Shimogamo used book fair.
明石さんとは　去年の夏
下鴨古本市のバイトで出会った
A year younger than I, said to be in the engineering department,
わたしの　１つ下の学年で
工学部に所属しているという
彼女は　何をするにも万事手回しがよく
and meticulously prepared at anything and everything she does,
it felt like one stare from her eyes and even a shoplifter would stay their hand.
じっと　何かをにらむような目つきは
万引犯も手が出せないと思われた
Oh, really?
へぇ～っ　そんななんだ
What do you do on vacations, Akashi-san?
明石さんは
休みの日って　何してんの？
Why do I have to tell you something like that?
何でそんなこと　あなたに
言わなきゃいけないの？
After that she was not someone who was asked her weekend plans.
その後　彼女に
週末の予定を聞くものはなかった
I sent her off with a fiery cheer of
"You just keep doing things your own way!"
わたしは　彼女に
「そのまま君の道を　ひた走れ！」と
熱いエールを送った
Good evening.
おこんばんは
What are you doing? Don't just barge in my room!
何をしてる！
勝手に入るな！
How dare you just stroll on in...
よくも　ヌケヌケと
It's a Castella.
カステラです
You can have it, so chill out.
これあげるから
機嫌　直してください
You giving someone something? That's rare...
珍しいではないか
お前が　物をくれるなんて
You can't get any lonelier than eating a giant Castella all by yourself.
大きなカステラを１人で食べるというのは
孤独の極地ですからね
人恋しさを　しみじみ
味わってほしくて　ででででっ！
Pining for a taste of a person's love...
Get out! I'm busy!
とっとと出ていけ！
俺は　忙しいんだ！！
ままっ　そう言わず
Is this really necessary?
帰れ！
Leave!
He probably came to visit the person in this boarding house known as "the master."
どうせ　あいつは
また　この下宿にいるという
師匠の所へでも
訪ねてきたんだろう
This Castella is surely the leftovers.
この　カステラも
その余り物に違いない
Nevertheless, just as Ozu said, a Castella like this is to be eaten together with someone.
とはいえ　まさしく小津の言うとおり
これだけのカステラは誰かと　一緒に食べたいものだ
Most definitely not Ozu. Perhaps with Akashi-san...
断じて　小津などではなく
例えば　明石さ…
あ
ほ
Even I was surprised that Akashi-san's name came to mind.
明石さんの　名前が出てきたのは
われながら　驚いた
Could that strange man who called himself a god and said he was heading out to Izumo
あの　みょうちくりんな神を名乗る男はわざわざ
出雲へ出掛けて　男女の縁結びをすると言っていたが
to decide the relationship between man and woman seriously be telling the truth?
本当にそんなこと　あってたまるか
Kannazuki. In other words, the 10th lunar month.
神無月　つまり旧暦の１０月
The myriad gods gather at Izumo, leaving vacant the various lands.
やおよろずの神々が出雲へ集まって
諸国がお留守になるということは
"Izumo"
多くの人が　知っていよう
This is quite well known. Even I know that.
わたしだって知っていた
Among those gods there are sure to be some of suitable peculiarity. That is not the issue.
その中には　相当みょうちくりんな
神様もおわしますに違いない
それは問題ない
The question I have often pondered is for what reason all those gods would gather at Izumo.
わたしが常々　疑問に思っていたのは
それだけの神様をわざわざ出雲へ集めて
何をやっているか
ということだった
And written right there it says that, at Izumo, after a boisterous and outspoken argument,
そこにはやおよろずの神々が出雲で
かんかんがくがくの論争結果…
男女の　縁を決めてると
書いてあった！
the myriad gods decide the relationships between man and woman!
"Don't they have anything better to do?"
Now that I'd ascertained the truth,
真偽を確かめるには　今から
２階に上がって神様に面会すればよい
it would be best for me to climb the stairs and see this god face to face.
But if that god from yesterday went...
しかし　それで昨日の神が
Ha ha, I got you good!
やーい　引っ掛かった　あはは…
...or something, I couldn't stand it.
などと言ってきたら
目も当てられない
I'd surely end up cursing myself and spending the second half of my life in a right mess.
己を　罵倒しながら残りの半生を送る羽目になるだろう
Even if that man is really a god,
よしんば　あの男が
本物の神様だったとして
it's not like I'm burning with passionate love;
さして熱烈な恋に　身を焦がしている
わけでもあるまいに
刹那的な寂しさから
赤の他人を求めるなど
it would go against my beliefs
to seek the comfort of a stranger from this transient loneliness.
わたしの信条に反する
Is it not because I scorn those inexcusable students
そうやって　孤独に耐え得ずガツガツと他人を求める
ふらちな学生たちを軽蔑すればこそ
who cannot bear the isolation and greedily seek out others
恋の邪魔者という限りなく　汚名に近い名を
はせてきたのではなかったか！
that I ran to the name of limitless notoriety as "one who hinders love"?
This guise of a barren, agonizing, wretched life...
不毛な苦闘に憂き身をやつし
Have not I finally reaped the victory close at hand from the endless number of defeats?
ついには限りなく　敗北に近い勝利を
収めたのではなかったか！
Would I, the one who hinders love, forgive myself for changing the way I live?
恋の邪魔者たる　わたしがいまさら
生き方を変えることなど許されるのか！
それこそ　クモの糸に
しがみついたところを
Or will it end with me proving entertainment to the gods as the spider's thread to which I cling snaps?
ぷつんと切られて　お釈迦様にエンターテインメント
を提供するのがオチではないか！
Then I'll become happy in your place.
じゃあ　あんたの代わりに
僕が　幸せになってやろ
Although I don't think Akashi-san would be fooled by a freaky youkai like Ozu,
あの　明石さんが小津のような
変態偏食妖怪にだまされるわけがないと思う一方
I feel like her compassion may be deep enough to find a monstrous man like him intriguing.
彼女には
あの　妖怪のような男でも
面白がれるだけの懐の深さが
あると思われた
If this continues and Ozu and Akashi-san become friendly with each other,
このまま　小津と明石さんが
懇ろになるようなことがあれば
わたし一人の
人恋しさの問題ではない
this will no longer be a problem of my own love;
it will become entangled with Akashi-san's future.
明石さんの将来に
かかわることだ
I felt like even my reason was crumbling to pieces like the Castella before me.
わたしの理性までがカステラのよう
にボロボロ崩れていくかに思えた
I'm not going to lose.
負けてたまるか！
人恋しさに負けてたまるか！
I'm not going to lose to pining for love!
The taste is definitely unmatched,
それはもう　無類の味なのだが
but unfortunately no one knows where they'll set up.
いかんせんどこへ　やって来るか分からない
神出鬼没のラーメン屋なのです
It's a ramen stand that comes and goes as it pleases.
You go there quite often, yes, Senpai?
先輩はよく行かれるのですね
ああ　わたしは
もう　鼻が利くからね
Well, I have a good nose.
空腹に耳を傾ければ
猫ラーメンの風鈴の音が聞こえてくる
When I'm hungry, if I cock my ear I can hear Neko Ramen's wind chime.
I would like to try eating there as well.
わたしも　食してみたいです
Let go! Let go, Akashi-san!
放せ！　放すんだ
明石さん！
I s-s-squished it‚ I squished it...
ハッ　むにゅっとしてました
むにゅっと
まあまあ　落ち着きたまえ
Now, now, calm down.
あっ　すみません
I apologize. I am not fond of moths.
ガは　苦手なんです
These are called Mochiguman, and they come in sets of five, but I have lost one.
これは　モチグマンといって
５匹で一揃いなのですが
１匹　なくしてしまって
Worry not! As this Earth is round, you are sure to meet once again!
心配するな
どうせ　地球は丸いのだ
いつか　また会える
Or if you'd like, I'll help search for it.
何なら　わたしが
捜してあげてもいい
それより　猫ラーメンに
連れていってください
I'd rather you take me to Neko Ramen.
If that's what you want.
そんなことなら
Then it's a promise.
約束ですよ
Promise? Ah, that's it.
約束って
そうか…
After careful analysis, indeed over-analysis of things,
わたしは　綿密に物事を分析して分析し尽くした揚げ句
I calmly execute a perfect countermeasure.
おもむろに　万全の対策を取る
むしろ　万全の対策が手遅れになることも
ちゅうちょせずに分析する男である
Or rather, I'm a man who doesn't hesitate to analyze to the point
where a perfect countermeasure becomes out of reach.
明石さんの人生　わたしの人生を
いく通りものパターンで分析し
Analyzing the number of different patterns of Akashi-san's life and my life,
誰が幸せになるべきで　誰がならないべきか
これは　すぐに結論が出た。
I quickly came to a conclusion as to who should become happy, and who should not.
But the most vexing question of all was whether I,
しかし　散々人の恋路を邪魔してきた　わたしが
who had hindered the path of love for countless people,
いまさら生き方を変えられるかというのが
最大の難問であった
could at this juncture change the way I live.
As a result of the life or death death struggle between love and reason that occurred within me,
人恋しさと理性が
くんずほぐれつの死闘を演じた結果
わたしは　寝不足の頭を抱え２１０号室のドアを　たたいた
I stumbled in my sleep-deprived state to knock on door 210.
Yeah?
You can't give her to Ozu!
小津は　いけません
わたしと明石さんにしてください
Give Akashi-san to me!
Right. Good, wait here a moment.
うん　よかろう
ちょっと待ちたまえ
Oh? Understood, yes...
そうか　分かった
了解　了解
今夜　８時前に
賀茂大橋の東詰で待ち合わせだ
Meet me before 8 PM on the east side of Kamo-oohashi.
Keep moving! Keep moving!
止まらないでください
Stopping on top of the bridge is dangerous!
橋の上で止まっては　危険です
今日は　五山か
Oh, so today is Gozan.
Now you will cross this Kamo-oohashi.
これから　君は
この賀茂大橋を渡る
When you do, Akashi-san will come walking from the other side.
すると　向こうから
明石さんが歩いてくる
Strike up a conversation about something and ask her out on a rendezvous.
何か話し掛けて
あいびきに誘いなさい
No way! I refuse!
無理です！
お断りする！
Stop your whining.
駄々を　こねるな
Something isn't right here!
おかしいじゃないか！
Weren't you going to Izumo and being a matchmaker?
あんた　出雲に出掛けて
縁結びしてくれるんじゃないのか
This sort of preparation is also important.
こうした　布石も大事だ
This is nothing but a frontal attack!
これだと
ただの正攻法ではないか！
Stop complaining and get out there.
あー　つべこべ言うな
行きなさい
Everything until now is water under the bridge!
これまでのことは　水に流す！
今こそ　ばら色のキャンパスライフへと
まい進するのだ！
Now's the time to push forward toward that rose-colored campus life!
あっ　先輩　こんばんは
Senpai, good evening.
You escaped safely last night?
昨日は　無事　逃げられましたか？
Thanks to you, yeah...
お…　おかげさまで　うん
五山ですか
Here for Gozan?
Yes yes.
そうそう！　うん
Bye!
あー　それでは
That went well.
いや　よくやった！
今日は　ここまで
That's enough for today.
恋路の走り方など　かけらも
学んでこなかった
I was able to come this far despite
learning not even the slightest bit about running the path of love!
わたしがここまで　できたのだ
これで　精いっぱい！
This was plenty!
Oh, hey!
おー　おい！
You just thought something like "that's enough for today," didn't you?
今日は　ここまでなんて
思ってるんじゃないでしょうな！
Don't defy the words of a god, hurry up and run along the path of love!
神の言葉に逆らわず
とっとと　恋路を走りやがれ！
Are you saying this was all your plot?
さては
全部　お前のたくらみか！
You made a wish to the god of matchmaking, right?
縁結びの神に
お願いしたでしょう？
I don't want your help!
大きな　お世話だ！
Now's the time to grab this opportunity!
今こそ　好機を　つかんでやれ！
If you don't make a serious move right now, I'm jumping!
今すぐ　ガツンと　いかないと
ここから　飛び降りてやる！
Wait a sec!
ちょっと待て！俺の恋路とお前が
飛び降りることと何の関係がある！
How do my love life and you jumping have anything to do with each other?
I'm not too sure myself.
僕にも　ちょっと分かりません
Ozu-san! The river is swollen.
小津さん！
水かさが増えてます
You will die if you jump in.
飛び降りると　死にます
You damn traitor!
この　裏切り者が！
You've got nowhere to run, Ozu!
もう逃げられんぞ　小津！
Revenge for the fireworks? But, this is...
花火の仕返しか？
しかし　これは？
Ozu-senpai, have you done some more mischief?
小津先輩！
また　何をやらかしたのですか！
You evil, good-for-nothing...
この　腐れ外道が！
Ozu!
小津！
You're a friend of his?
こいつも仲間か！？
いや　わたしは　小津と関係ない
Me? I don't know Ozu at all...
Don't!
やめろ！　ありゃ！
I can't shake off the feeling of regret
あの運命の時計台前でテニスサークル「キューピット」
を選んだことへの後悔の念は　振り払えない
for choosing tennis circle "Cupid" in front of that fateful clock tower.
If then I had chosen some other circle I would have surely spent quite a different two years.
あのとき
ほかのサークルを選んでいれば
わたしは　もっと　別の２年間を
送っていただろう
Perhaps I could have grasped
幻の至宝といわれる「ばら色のキャンパスライフ」を
手に握っていたかもしれない
the mystical treasure that is known as that "rose-colored campus life".
tengoku iku tame mainichi kosotto
天国　いくため　毎日こそっと
In order to go to heaven. Everyday, I quietly
naishou de ii koto shiteta kedo
内緒で　いいこと　してたけど
and privately do good deeds
namida hitohira
涙ひとひら
But a single teardrop
atama kurakura
あたまくらくら
Sends my head spinning
ano ko hasuppa koi dorobou
あの娘　はすっぱ　恋泥棒
That stupid girl, that love thief
watashi kenage ii hito
わたしけなげ　いいひと
I am a good and pure person
kanawanakatta koigokoro
叶わなかった恋心
My longing heart was not fulfilled
kamisama doushite
神様どうして
Why, god?
yurusanakucha koi dorobou
ゆるさなくっちゃ恋泥棒
I must forgive her. That love thief
ano ko tabun ii hito
あの娘たぶん　いいひと
Maybe she was actually a good person
wasurenakucha konna koto
忘れなくっちゃこんなこと
I have to forget all these things
watashi wa tengoku
わたしは天国
I'm in heaven
yurusanakucha
ゆるさなくっちゃ
I have to forgive her!